During the Second World War, the
government of Canada commissioned
artists to record the activities of the
Canadian military.
Some were sent to Europe. Others painted
the home front. In all, more than 5,000
paintings [music] were produced.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I remember being interviewed to see what
part of the military I should fit into
properly.
And this personnel officer was um making
out this questionnaire, and he asked me
what I was
doing in civilian life.
I told him I was an artist, a commercial
artist, and a very good artist.
And I noticed he wrote down on the form
no trade.
>> [laughter]
[music]
>> At the beginning of the war, the
government is reluctant to spend money
on a war art program, having just funded
the establishment of the National Film
Board.
When Canada's artists hold their first
national conference in 1941, every
Allied country has established a war art
program, except Canada.
The artists remind the government that
Canada was the first country to
establish a program in the First World
War.
It was one of the most important war art
collections in existence.
But after the war, it had gone into
storage and was rarely seen.
>> Fire!
>> A.Y. Jackson, a veteran of the program,
could see why the government was in no
rush to fund another,
but argued that the artists' view was
needed, not so much as a record, but as
an expression of the period.
>> I didn't know if there was anything like
the war artists, but I thought I'm going
to get in the army and I'm going to
paint. That's
um that was an absolute thing I had in
my head. And when I began, I did a diary
that is now in archives.
And it's maybe the best war art I did it
it because it was every day and it
starts out with I pretended it was a
paper.
And it starts [music] out with a
headline, "Girl takes drastic step."
>> Canada's artists sign up for war like
other Canadians.
New Brunswick artist Miller Brittain
sketches scenes of a bomber crew's
everyday life.
Sells them to his mates for $5, which he
never collects.
Commander Harold Beament uses snatches
of off-duty time to record the personnel
and routines on his own ship.
Others put aside their brushes.
Robert Hyndman joins the Air Force.
His movie star looks make him a natural
for a recruiting poster.
Courage and idealism.
>> My life, my whole life was dedicated to
painting before this war at all. And I
was intending to be a be an artist, you
know, not a not an aviator, but when the
war came along that's I naturally had to
uh
to do go do something, so I
I tried to get in
as a pilot, which worked out.
>> I went in and I had a medical.
And they passed [music] me and then I
and I started down to go outside and a
man stopped me at the door like a guard
and he said [music]
you have to have a pass. And I
What what is this, you know, I've got
myself into a jail here.
I said I can't go on with this. I hate
[music] this. It's horrible. And the
next day they took me down to the
basement
gave me a green uniform and a hair net
and I had to [music] wait on the
soldiers, you know, give them donuts and
coffee. And uh
I didn't mind it as I started to think
this is okay, you know, except for the
hair net cuz I was vain.
And by the third day, I don't think you
could pull me out of that army.
>> Three years into the war and there is
still no war art program.
From London, Vincent Massey Canada's
High Commissioner and long-time patron
of the arts presses his friend Mackenzie
King for a program.
The camera, he says, is necessarily
limited in its use.
Massey convinces King that the work of
artists is also required if there is to
be an adequate record of Canada's war
activities.
Within months, the first artists, having
completed basic officer training,
make final preparations to go to Europe.
The director of the National Gallery,
H.O. McCurry, is to select the
participants with the help of eminent
artists such as A.Y. Jackson and Arthur
Lismer.
Joining them are the historical officers
of the Army, Navy, and Air Force.
The Army representative is the First
World War veteran, Colonel A. Fortescue
Dugood.
Dugood expects the art to be accurate,
as he informs one artist, right down to
the placement of the screw heads on the
Bren gun.
All Dugood's suggestions are foolish,
Jackson grumbles to McCurry,
and yet to turn them all down will make
an enemy of him,
and that would end everything.
One of the artists that Dugood champions
is an infantry officer, Alex Colville.
>> Well, Dugood and I got on well.
I suppose Dugood's idea of what a war
artist should be doing and my idea of it
coincided more or less. I would want
everything to be right and uh
all my stuff was really quite
painstakingly accurate.
>> But McCurry is not impressed.
There is a work of Colville's in the
present Academy exhibition, and
personally, I think it is too dreadful
for words. Our reputations will be mud
to future generations if better artists
are not selected.
H.O. McCurry
>> [laughter]
>> Well, you see, I never I never knew
either of these either McCurry or
Jackson at all well, but I didn't like
them.
So, there you are. You
>> Summer 1943
The Canadian Army invades Sicily and
marches up the Italian Peninsula.
With the troops is Will Ogilvie.
Canada's first war artist to see action.
Ogilvie notes in his diary
You can't paint a war, but most artists
felt it was their duty to express what
the men were going through.
>> [music]
>> Ogilvie's watercolors are hailed by
military historians and Vincent Massey
as one of the most important pictorial
records of the war.
The enthusiastic reception is tempered
by one dissenting voice.
His work is not liked. It is regarded as
being too slight, too casual, and not
studied enough.
Colonel A. Fortescue Duguid
Ogilvie is joined by Lauren P. Harris.
Lauren the lesser, as he calls himself
in deference to his famous Group of
Seven father.
Grateful for the work, Harris wonders
about the program's objectives.
Couldn't a camera do this?
>> I can remember even mentioning that to
Mr. Massey.
He said Well,
there is a point because consciously or
unconsciously when you do a sketch, uh
um
you put into it your feeling about it.
Whereas the camera is almost a
mechanical device that just captures
what's there, but you can express
[music] it in other ways as as to how
you feel.
>> Of all the artists in the program,
Charles Comfort is seen as the most
technically accomplished and
resourceful.
The operatic quality, in one artist's
view, makes his works a natural for
recruitment posters.
The image of a gun sight,
a strange fusion of machine surfaces,
the delicate transparent tracery of the
nets,
then a flower-like pink-edged flame of
instant blooming,
a shocking, numbing sound, and a
concussion that jumps my equipment clear
off the ground.
One felt suspended helplessly in some
dense, exhausting element where sound,
and sound only, existed.
Charles Comfort.
>> [music]
>> A destroyer's decks have few workable
spots for painting.
The air is usually full of spray.
The vibration from her powerful engines
and propellers so great that putting a
line of brush stroke on paper or canvas
is often an exciting gamble.
Painting at sea in wartime becomes
simply a matter of what wind, weather,
the enemy, and the ship herself makes
possible.
The convoy is a beautiful sight rolling
and plunging, a thrilling performance
put on for our special benefit with the
war far away.
Until action [music] stations are
sounded as possibly somebody gets it.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Oh my.
Oh my my my.
All my children.
>> Navy artist Leonard Brooks sees his
wartime watercolors and oils for the
first time in 50 years.
>> Rough weather on a minesweeper.
Well, there you are. That's what it felt
like.
There's the captain and boy that
on the bridge there and it's really
being tossed around.
Hollering down and
can imagine how that was being tossed.
How the hell I painted that in the
with that ship tossing around it. But,
that's obviously painted on the spot,
you see.
There's puncher.
There's puncher here.
And you can see she's a a pretty good
size carrier.
And uh that's a nice moody dirty looking
sky and uh
I rather like that one. Now that's a
more That's a studio painting which I
would work out later.
In all these is I'm trying to get the
moods at the feeling
of the place.
And you see you don't see
cannons firing and all that stuff. A lot
of that's what is going on. It's this
kind of stuff that was day after day
that was the navy. It wasn't all this
gung-ho action.
And that's what's different than the
army where in Italy there's That's what
So they painted that that kind of thing.
>> Navy artist Tom Wood.
I'll tell you something. Very rarely did
you see action in the Hollywood sense of
the word.
You're stationed on a convoy of about
100 ships. You're aware of the historic
event and you had the good fortune to be
involved in a major chunk of human
history.
But you're 21 days aboard this ship.
You really might [music] say you're in
jail for 21 days.
I was lucky being a war artist.
But the guys that were on that ship were
there for 3 years doing that.
Back and forth. Back and forth.
Tom Wood.
>> Unlike most of the war artists, Jack
Nichols makes no quick on board
sketches.
Holds what he sees in his mind until the
quiet concentration of the studio.
What I remember most about the war is
the feeling of being overwhelmed.
>> I remember seeing a ship being hit
and then the people fell into the sea.
I couldn't imagine introducing sunlight
into any of these pictures.
I think of black and white as color
and sometimes it gives off color.
>> [music]
>> I don't try to describe things.
You can't put what I do into words.
That's why I do paintings.
>> For 3 years I really was a terrible
burden on the Canadian taxpayer. I did
nothing but so eat I think as far as I
remember and wait on table or in
canteen. I was in the army show. I was
moved all over the place. But always I
hitchhiked to Ottawa and I'd go up to
the National Gallery and practically get
on my knees and say, "Mr. McCurry, make
me a war artist."
>> There is no official policy, but women
are not selected as official war [music]
artists.
Peggy Nichol MacLeod paints on a
National Gallery commission.
>> She painted wonderful impressionistic
pictures of naval women marching down
the street or standing in front of her.
She just took the brush, filled it with
different colors, and went blop blop
blop for the medals.
When the commanding officer saw them,
she was furious.
Louise Comfort
>> McLeod's commission is to cover the
activities of the women's Royal Canadian
Navy and the Canadian Women's Army
Corps, the Wrens and the CWACs.
Two months' work, according to McCurry,
with a small honorarium of $300 a month,
McCurry inquires coyly, "Be beneath your
notice?"
>> To me, it represented a sort of painting
holiday, orgy sans housework. Of course,
it's a year's work or more, not 2
months.
Peggy Nicole MacLeod
>> Artist Paraskeva Clark also receives a
commission from McCurry.
He asks her for a few canvases of an
inspirational nature.
"I'm not awfully anxious," he writes,
"to have more studies of girls working
in kitchens, offices, and that sort of
thing."
Clark replies,
"There are no dramatic subjects among
the CWACs. Being a CWAC means throwing
off the eternal chores and drudgery of a
woman's life.
There is drama," she wrote, "among the
women who stayed home, carrying on some
job, some responsibility, [music]
plus their usual home duties,
with their hearts full of constant pain,
longing, and sorrow for their men gone
fighting."
Artist Fred Taylor
volunteers to contribute his talent to
the war effort.
He proposes a series of war production
paintings. The government turns him
down.
His leftist politics make him suspect.
>> I'm determined to break through by any
means, however distasteful to me.
>> He must turn to his brother, the wealthy
capitalist E.P. Taylor, for help.
>> I did so reluctantly by exerting private
influence.
24 hours later, I was at work in a
Montreal tank arsenal.
Management thought I must be some kind
of government or labor spy.
Labor thought I must be a government or
management spy.
Interrogations were usually conducted by
horse shouting above the roar of
machinery.
Who are you working for? Who is paying
you? Why are you doing it?
The first few days I spent in each shop
were exceedingly trying until I had
something to show.
>> Fred Taylor.
>> In spite of his energy and persistence,
or perhaps because of it,
Taylor is never officially commissioned
to do war work.
After the war, he gifts the best of his
paintings to the National Gallery.
>> [applause]
>> Not everyone could get used to the war.
It was just happening to you.
War artist Campbell Tinning is to recall
later.
He felt that his real life was on hold.
T. R. MacDonald preferred to deal with
the war indirectly,
seeking images that reflected the
atmosphere of wartime London.
Miller Britain escapes the pressure of
his daily bomber runs
by painting scenes of the off-duty lives
of Canadian airmen.
Having achieved the Billy Bishop dream
of his boyhood,
fighter pilot Robert Hindman
turns from flying Spitfires to painting
Spitfires as an official war artist.
>> The memories of of the whole business of
of flying in a squadron,
you know, it was such a tremendously
different way of of being alive.
You get up and have breakfast and then
go over to France
and try to get into trouble or cause
trouble
and come back for lunch.
On one occasion that
our squadron commander had a direct hit,
I think probably on his bomber or his
aircraft, and he just blew up into 8,000
pieces.
All I could see was thousands of little
pieces of
the size of a pin
floating through space, little black
bits of of him
and his aircraft.
And uh was one of those bright lovely
days and flying back over the channel.
I just said to myself, I hate this war.
I was just filled with disgust.
Something really really awful was is a
terrible feeling.
>> Their Excellencies the Governor General
and Her Royal Highness Princess Alice
opened the first nationwide Army Art
Exhibit in Canada.
A. Y. Jackson, Arthur Lismer, A. J.
McCurry, and Only Masson served as
judges.
They awarded second prize Lance Corporal
Molly Lamb of Vancouver for her pay
parade.
>> [music]
>> And first prize, a $100 war bond, was
won by Sapper Bruno Bobak for his
cross-country convoy.
>> As a result of his first prize at the
Army Art Exhibition,
Bruno Bobak is invited by Massey to
become a war artist
after the 6-week officers training
course.
>> The 6-week period during that course was
just the time when the D-Day landings
were taking place and the actual
um
unit platoon of engineers that I was
really part of before I became a war
artist, a good many of them were killed
just on that first day of uh landing in
Europe. And uh I'm not a very
um
uh brilliant guy when it comes to
military
survivals and I'm pretty sure I would
have been one of those that was dead on
the beach.
>> Coming in after the first assault wave,
the army's [music] Orville Fisher is
among the artists recording their
impressions of the first anxious days of
the Canadians' return to the beaches of
France.
>> Good part of the war art subjects appear
to be
uh
the results of battles rather than the
battles themselves. So, there'd be ruins
of buildings uh or people uh begging or
people hurt or people injured. And I
remember
things like uh nuns coming out of a
convent all dressed in black and looking
into this weird kind of landscape. It
just seemed to me such a strange
combination of contrast between the sort
of
uh deserted landscape uh
We were close to the front. Front was
everywhere. That's the problem. I
remember once um
driving and we came across crossroads
somewhere in Holland.
I said, "I think we've gone too far to
the driver." I said, "Those look like
two young German soldiers standing there
on the corner."
Well, at that point we
whipped around in a hurry and we were
just about as surprised as these two
German soldiers were and we were
actually in the on enemy lines, which
happened quite frequently because it
wasn't like the First World War where
you had a line that said this is one
side and this is the other side. Indeed,
some of our artists did get
trapped behind enemy lines. I think
George Pepper was one of them.
>> [music]
>> The apt title of a painting made by
Captain [music] George Pepper of Toronto
is Hitler's Youth.
During one of his painting expeditions,
Captain Pepper was caught behind the
German lines.
>> [music]
>> His only food for 10 days was a chicken
shot with his revolver lander.
The fowl had to be consumed raw.
>> As a war artist, my strongest memory is
probably the one where I
was being strafed by a low-flying plane
and
almost got hit and I remember jumping
straight into an old slit trench that
was uh
handy
right in front of me and halfway down I
could see I was falling onto a dead
soldier.
And when I hit him, it went
but I was too chicken to get out.
>> Through towns and villages wasted by the
retreating enemy,
the Canadians moved doggedly forward
into the freezing rain and mud of the
North European winter.
With the Third Canadian Division in
Holland,
is Alex Colville.
>> I had been in the army almost exactly 2
years when I was [music] made a war
artist.
You know, I I guess I had I felt
pleasure for two reasons. Probably, to
be frank, number one is the
diminution of the chance of being
killed, you know. And number two, simple
pleasure at being able to paint again.
And to be paid for it, which seemed
astonishing to me.
>> Colville looks back on his war work as
an apprenticeship,
sketching or painting something every
day, regardless of his moods or the
weather.
>> [music]
[music]
>> You know, you
you drive by something and you think,
"This is interesting."
Uh
you couldn't exactly say why you think
it's interesting, but I'd stop and
get out of the jeep and make a drawing
of it or something. So, you're operating
really uh to a large degree on instinct.
>> Accumulating a precise daily record of
his particular corner of the war,
but on the lookout for something that
would take his art beyond the
repertorial.
>> [music]
>> Many of Colville's paintings begin as
sketches, evolving into composite scenes
that the artist has never actually
witnessed.
Yet, shades of Colonel Doogood, physical
detail is rigorously observed.
>> The job of a corporal, for instance, the
leading figure in that is a corporal and
the number one brand had the Bren gun,
which was our most advanced light
machine gun. The corporal,
the head, I realized more after it was
all done and years later that I had uh
I had depicted my father who had been a
foreman of a riveting gang who were also
doing very dangerous work and often got
killed.
>> "I didn't always feel pleased with my
stuff," Colville admits.
"But this one, Infantry near Nijmegen,
had more than just accuracy." [music]
>> Nobody had it worse than the infantry
people.
Day after day, week after week, month
after month, no sleep,
nothing more than a couple of hours of
stats [music]
sleep, and cold, wet,
dirty.
When you look back on it, you think,
"How the hell did they do it?"
>> I remember somebody saying, "Oh, if it's
really cold and you're doing some
watercolors,
why don't you just add a little bit of
salt to the water and and then it won't
freeze." Well,
I tried that several times and it never
really worked because as soon as you
brought the artwork
indoors or into your tent where it was
warm, the whole thing would melt and
slide off the paper
cuz it only looked good while it was
frozen.
>> [laughter]
>> I ruined a lot of watercolors that way.
>> Among the first artists to be considered
for the war art program was airman
Miller Brittain.
He turned them down.
>> At the time I was about to start air
crew training.
After marching, scrubbing floors and
shoveling snow for several months.
I was flattered to be included
but I felt it was not for me until I had
tasted war in the air.
>> While Brittain flew
Paul Goranson documented and gains the
admiration of the Air Force by his
complete disregard for danger in making
his paintings.
After 2 years of active duty as a bomb
aimer
Miller Brittain [music] writes to
McCurry that he is ready to be a war
artist but not without misgivings.
>> I wonder how far it is possible
for a person like [music] me who is
fundamentally interested in human beings
to capture the sinister fairy land of a
target on canvas or paper.
A German city under bombing
often looked like a casket of [music]
jewels
opening up in some Walt Disney film.
It was terrible.
It was wicked.
But there was a fascinating beauty to
it.
My target picture
looks like the real thing, they say.
In fact at the moment I feel like
putting my foot through it.
Miller Brittain
>> I think he was
quite destroyed by the war.
You know, he really had a hard time ever
coming back.
He was one of the most sensitive people
I I knew.
And I think he suffered. And he would
have wanted to stay with his group, him
with his little poems of Blake in his
pocket, you know.
Quite a man.
>> The end of the war finds war artist Abba
Bayefsky
stationed just a few miles from a German
concentration camp
liberated by the British.
>> During the war, I saw people
uh at the airfields, I saw people not
returning from operations. And all of
that's very touching and very moving.
But the one area
that
I have never forgotten and is still with
me to this day is Belsen concentration
camp.
>> When I got there,
I realized, you know, that this was a
moment of decision for me.
You know, my life
as a Jewish young man
had known anti-Semitism.
Nothing of this sort. I realized that
this is where I should be.
I wasn't assigned to that, but that's
where I was and where I intended to
stay.
>> There are people who don't like to look
at them.
And you don't feel too upset by looking
at them, but I think the reasons why I
did it I trust are clear.
My intention was to make sure that this
was
put on record.
And that's what
I think I did.
>> I just Jackson and I just clicked. We
were great great friends and we'd laugh
and we talked about war and peace. And
he'd smoke away. He never smoked before
12:00 in the morning and then then he
never stopped. I showed him my war diary
and he thought it was very funny.
>> [music]
>> I think that's really what gave him the
idea, you know, that it would be nice to
be have me as a war artist.
>> As Molly Lamb heads overseas for a
6-month assignment with Canada's
post-war army in Europe,
many of the overseas war artists are
heading home
to complete their work and to be
photographed by Malak before heading off
into civilian life.
>> I like Charles Comfort. He was a very
sweet man, very um proud of himself.
And I remember when we all got back to
Ottawa, we had to go with McCurry
and have a photograph taken of all of
army war artists together. And I
remember seeing Charles just before the
photographer got busy going
>> [laughter]
>> like that to his eyebrow. But he was
very vain, but he was kind and he was um
brilliant technically, I must say, I
think.
>> Harold, it's very easy for me to say
whose work I
feel
has been underestimated, never given its
due.
That was Charles Goldhammer's drawings
that he did for airmen who were burned.
And I don't think anyone [music] else,
including Aba Bayefsky,
did work of that intensity.
>> The story goes that when someone asked
Goldhammer why he sketched such hard
scenes to look at,
>> [music]
>> he replied,
"I was asked to go either on an aircraft
carrier or to a hospital,
and the aircraft carrier didn't interest
me.
I knew the food was good in the
hospital,
Canadian food, and they had real meat
and ice cream."
>> Harold,
I'm not so sure I I
>> [laughter]
>> I
I would uh
I I I think that sounds like a story.
I think that uh Charlie didn't care that
much for ice cream.
>> The artists returned to a major
exhibition at the National Gallery.
For the younger artists, it helped
establish their careers as painters,
even though they were still in their
early 20s.
>> The Governor General was there and
most of the war office were high as
kites. I remember Will Ogilvie had sent
some running down the sides of his
mouth.
>> Missing from the exhibition, however,
were Charles Goldhammer's sketches of
burnt airmen.
An oversight that greatly disappointed
him.
>> The war itself was
a revelation to me. It opened up
horizons for me. It opened up a
universality that I never had before. I
mean, I was a pretty
rustic, local guy back in Canada,
although I thought I was sophisticated.
>> It changed my life
because I was just beginning to live.
I was young.
So,
I never knew any other kind of life. I
mean, I this was the beginning for me.
And it's it's never stopped.
You know, I'm 76 at this point.
And I'm still painting.
>> I enjoyed it, but at the same time
you you have a dimension of fear and and
a little tension of all those that sort
of thing.
And uh
but you can't help being excited by
flying a Spitfire
in action.
It's a a great moment in life.
>> It was a horrible war, and I think that
um
anyone that escaped like I did, and
Paris gave a clock is right. It was
easier to be in the quacks than to be at
home waiting for some guy that might
never come home, you know.
I think that's true.
>> Of her painting when Johnny comes
marching home
Peggy Bacon McLoud wrote though drafted
for years into the army
Johnny returns to find everything the
same. The life [clears throat] of the
block doesn't change much. Girls marry
neighborhood boys take flats across the
street or nearby.
Families remain for years.
>> There was something wonderful about the
faces of those young men in those days.
They
they had a
somehow a greater depth than
one sees in the average way of life.
>> All of us I think painted things that
were much more more grounded and earthy
as opposed to the the
you know, an heroic statement. The
posters for the war were heroic. You
know, people were marching and their
arms were forward and their helmets and
their guns and so on.
But they were posters.
They weren't paintings of an actuality
that I saw.
>> You did what you could do and I recorded
everything that I could and some of the
pictures were rotten some were good.
But I kept at it.
And sometimes I was very frustrated
because I didn't do what I'd like to
have done.
>> I happen to think that the judgment of
time
is
just and acute, you know, proper.
And so
I find this encouraging actually. Maybe
that's why I believe that because it is
an encouraging kind of an upbeat
thought.
But I I think this is actually what does
happen.
And so, it's kind of comforting to think
that the stuff that's really just junk
will go
because there's a lot of God knows,
really.
>> Women having gas drill, and they're all
standing there with these snouts on, and
one of them can't get it on, and it's in
the snow, and it's a little bit
subjective, but it's funny, and I think
it's a good painting. It's white and red
brick and khaki. That's I think it works
quite well as a painting. And then the
way I think it was a
that the whole making fun of oneself has
to be really funny so you could be
serious about it.
>> After the war,
some of us survived, and some of us got
a larger reputation,
and then some of us just faded away and
disappeared.
But, whatever whatever happened, we're
in the history books, and
we're there forever now.
>> [singing]
[music]
[singing]
>> Official war artist Molly Lamb and
official war artist Bruno Bobak were
married in 1946
on their return from overseas. [music]
Best man at the wedding was official war
artist Aba Bayefsky.
>> [singing]
[music]
[singing]
>> on straight
with you.
>> [music]
>> There's a long, [singing and music] long
night awaiting
until my dreams all
come true. [singing and music]
Till the day that I'll
be walking down that
long, long trail.